<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Modal for the French king, or The memorable acts of Henry the Eight extirpating popery and introducing the Protestant religion, collected out of the most authentick records of the most memorable things, referring to the reformation, for publick good.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 91KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A51054</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12279923</idno>
  <idno type="VID">58659</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2248552859</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing M2313</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R15623</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">12279923</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A51054)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 58659)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 871:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Modal for the French king, or The memorable acts of Henry the Eight extirpating popery and introducing the Protestant religion, collected out of the most authentick records of the most memorable things, referring to the reformation, for publick good.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 5-36 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for R. Baldwin,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1682.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Henry --  VIII, --  King of England, 1491-1547.</term>
               <term type="corporate_name">England and Wales. --  Sovereign (1509-1547 : Henry VIII).</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Protestantism.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Great Britain --  History --  Henry VIII, 1509-1547.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-06 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-10 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-10 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:58659:1"/>
            <p>A MODAL FOR THE French King: OR THE MEMORABLE ACTS OF Henry the Eight; EXTIRPATING POPERY AND INTRODUCING <hi>The Protestant Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Collected out of the most Authentick Records of the most memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable things, referring to the</hi> Reformation, <hi>For publick Good.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for R. <hi>Baldwin,</hi> 1682.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:58659:2"/>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:58659:2"/>
            <div type="proclamation">
               <head>King <hi>Henry</hi> VIII. his Proclamation for the Abolishing the Usurped Power of the Pope; as it is recorded in <hi>Fox</hi> his Book of Martyrs, <hi>Fol.</hi> 335. <hi>Vol.</hi> 2.</head>
               <p>TRusty and Well-beloved, We greet you well.<note place="margin">The Kings Proclamation against the Pope.</note> And whereas not onely upon good, and just, and vertuous grounds and respects, edified upon the Laws of holy Scripture, dy due consultation, deliberation, advisement, and consent, as well of all other our Nobles and Commons Temporal, as also Spiritual, assembled in our high Court of Parliament, and by Authority of the same, we have by good and wholsom Laws and Statutes made for this purpose, extirped, abolished, separated, and seclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded out of this our Realm, the Abuses of the Bishop of Rome, his Authority and Iurisdiction of long time usurp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, as well upon us and our Realm, as upon all other Kings and Princes and their Realms, (like as they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves have confessed and affirmed;) but also for as much as our said Nobles and Commons, both Spiritual and Temporal, assembled in our high Court of Parliament, have upon good, lawful, and vertuous grounds, and for the publick weal of this our Realm, by one whole Assent granted, annexed, knit, and united to the Crown Imperial of the same, the Title, Dignity,<note place="margin">The Style of <hi>Supreme Head</hi> annexed to the Crown of England.</note> and Style of <hi>Supreme Head or Governour in earth, immediately under God, of the Church of England,</hi> as we be and undoubtedly have hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to been. Which Title and Style both the Bishops and Elergy of this our Realm have not onely in Convocation assembled, consented, recognized, and approved lawfully and justly to appertain unto us, but also by Word, Oath, Profession, and Writing under their Signs and Seals, have confessed, ratified, corroborated, and confirmed the same, utterly renouncing all other Oaths and Obedience to any other forein Potentates, and all forein Iurisdictions and Powers, as well of the said Bishop of Rome, as of all other whatsoever they be, as by their said Professions and Writings corroborated with the Subscription of their Names, and Appension of their Seals more plainly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth. We let you to wit, that calling to our remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance the Power, Charge, and Commission given unto us of Almighty God, and upon a vehment love and affection toward our loving and faithful Subjects, perceiving right
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:58659:3"/> well what great rest, quietness, and tranquillity of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science, and manifold other commodities might insurge and arise unto them, if that the said Bishops and other of the Clergy of this our Realm should set forth, declare, and preach to them the true and syncere Word of God, and without all manner colour, dissimulation, and hypocrisie, manifest and publish the great and innumerable Enormi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and Abuses which the said Bishop of Rome, as well in the Title and Style, as also in Authority and Iurisdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, of long time unlawfully and unjustly hath usurped upon us and our Progenitors, and also other Christian Princes; have therefore addressed our Letters unto the Bishop of the Diocefe, straitly charging and commanding him in the same, that not onely he in his own proper per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son shall declare, teach, and preach unto the People, forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with upon the receipt of our said Letters unto him direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, every Sunday and other high Feasts through the year, the true, mere, and syncere Word of God; and that the same Title, Style, and Iurisdiction of Supreme Head appertaineth onely to our Crown and Dignity Royal. Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise as the said Bishop, and all other the Bishops of our Realm, have by Oath affirmed, and confirmed by Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scription of their Names, and setting to their Seals, but also give warning, monition, and charge, to all manner Abbats, Priors, Deans, Archdeacons, Provosts, Parsons, Vicars, Curats, and all other Ecclesiastical Persons within his said Diocese, as well to teach, preach, publish, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare, in all manner Churches our aforesaid just Title, Style, and Iurisdiction, every Sunday and high Feast through the year, and further to monish and command all other Schoolmasters within his said Diocese, to instruct and teach the same unto the Children committed unto them; as also to cause all manner Prayers, Orisons, Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bricks, Canons of Mass-beeks, and all other Books in the Churches, wherein the said Bishop of Rome is named, or his presumptuous and proud Pomp and Authority prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, utterly to be abolished, eradicate, and razed out, and his Name and Memory to be never more (except to his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tumely and reproach) remembred,<note place="margin">The Popes Name a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d Memo y abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ed.</note> but perpetually sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressed and obscured. And finally to desist and leave out all such Articles as be in the general Sentence, which is usu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y accustomed to be read, four times in the year, and do t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd to the glory and advancement of the Bishop of Rome, his Name, Title and Iurisdiction.</p>
               <p>Whereupon we esteeming and reputing you to be of such singular and vehment zeal and affection toward the glory of Almighty God, and of so faithful, loving, and obedient heart towards us, as you will not onely do and accomplish
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:58659:3"/> with all power, wisdom, diligence, and labour, whatsoever should or might be to the preferment and setting forward of Gods Word, but also practise, study, and endeavour your self, with all your policy, wit, power, and good will, to am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plifie, defend and maintain all such Interest, Right, Title, Style, Iurisdiction, and Authority, as is in any wise ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertaining unto us, our Dignity, and Prerogative, and Crown Imperial of this our Realm; have thought good and expedient not onely to signifie unto you by these our Letters the particularities of the Charge, Monition, and Commandment given by us unto the said Bishop, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is specified, but also to require and straitly charge and command you, upon pain of your Allegeance, and as you sha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l avoid our high Indignation and Displea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure at your utmost peril, laying apart all vain affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, resp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s, or other carnal considerations, and setting onely before your eyes the mirror of truth, the glory of God, the dignity of your Sovereign Lord and King, and the great concord and unity, and inestimable pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit and utility, that shall by the due execution of the premisses ensue to your self, and all other faithful and lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Subjects, ye make or cause to be made diligent search and wait, and especially in every place of your Shirewick, whether the said Bishop do truly and syn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely, and without all manner cloke, colour, or dissimu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, execute, and accomplish our will and command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as is aforesaid. And in case ye shall hear, perceive, and approvably understand and know, that the said Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shop, or any other Ecclesiastical Person within his Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cese, do omit and leave undone any part or parcel of the premisses, or else in the execution and setting forth of the same, do coldly and feignedly use any manner sinister addition, wrong interpretation, or painted colour; then we straitly charge and command you, that forthwith upon any such default, negligence, or dissimulation of the said Bishop, or any other Ecclesiastical Person of his Diocese, contrary to the true tenour, meaning, and effect of the said Charge by us to him appointed aforesaid, ye do make in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delayedly, and with all speed and diligence, declaration, and advertisement, to us and our Council, of the said de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fault, and of the behaviour, manner, and fashion of the same.</p>
               <p>And forasmuch as we upon singular trust and assured confidence which we have in you, and for the special love and zeal we suppose and think ye bear toward us and the publick and common Wealth, Vnity, and Tranquillity of this our Realm, have specially elected and chosen you among so many for this purpose, and have reputed you
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:58659:4"/> such men, as unto whose wisdom, discretion, truth, and fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, we might commit a matter of such great weight, mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and importance, as whereupon the Vnity and Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quillity of our Realm doth consist. If ye should contrary to our expectation and trust which we have in you, and against your duty and Allegeance towards us, neglect or omit to do with all your diligence and wisdom, whatsoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver shall be in your power, for the due performance of our mind and pleasure to you before declared in this behalf, or halt or stumble at any part or specialty of the same; be ye assured that we like a Prince of Iustice will so extremely punish you for the same, that all the World besides shall take by you example and beware, contrary to their Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance, to disobey the lawful Commandment of their So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereign Lord and Prince in such things, as by the faithful execution whereof, ye shall not onely advance the Honour of Almighty God, and set forth the Majesty and Imperial Dignity of your Sovereign Lord, but also bring an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>estimable weal, profit, and commodity, unity and tranquil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity to all the common State of this our Realm, whereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to both by the Laws of God, Nature, and Man, ye be ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly bound.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>Given under our Signet at our Palace of Westminster,</hi>
                     <date>the 9. <hi>day of June.</hi>
                     </date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
               <trailer>Furthermore, that no man shall cavil or surmise this fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal fall and ruine of the Pope to have come rashly upon the Kings own partial affection, or by any sensual temerity of a few, and not by the grave and advised Iudgment, Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation, and Consent, generally and publickly, as well of the Nobles and Commons Temporal, as also upon sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantial grounds, and the very strength of truth, by the discussion and consultation of the Spiritual and most Learned Persons in this Realm. It shall be requisite moreover to these premisses, to adjoyn the words and testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies also of the Bishops own oaths and profession made to the King, yielding and rendering unto him onely the Style of <hi>Supreme Head next under Christ of the Church of England;</hi> all other Service, Subjection, and Obedience to be given to any other forein Potentate, which should be prejudicial to the Kings Highness in this behalf being ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded, and that both frankly and freely of their own volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary motion, and also upon the faith and fidelity of their Priesthood, as by their own words and handwriting may appear, in form as hereunder followeth.</trailer>
            </div>
            <div xml:lang="lat" type="oath">
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:58659:4"/>
               <head>The Oath of <hi>Stephen Gardener</hi> Bishop of <hi>Winchester,</hi> made to King <hi>Henry</hi> VIII.</head>
               <p>EGO Stephanus Wintoniensis Episcopus, pure, sponte,<note place="margin">The Oath of <hi>Stephen Garde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner</hi> to the King.</note> &amp; absolute, in verbo Pontificio, profiteor ac spondeo illustrissi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mae vestrae Regiae Majestati, singulari ac summo Domino meo &amp; Patrono, Henrico Dei gratia Angliae &amp; Franciae Regi, Fidei De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fensori, Domino Hiberniae, atque in terris Ecclesiae Anglicanae Supremo immediate sub Christo Capiti, quod posthac nulli ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terno Imperatori, Regi, Principi, aut Praelato, nec Romano Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifici (quem Papam vocant) fidelitatem &amp; obedientiam, &amp;c.</p>
               <div xml:lang="eng" type="translation">
                  <head>Translated into <hi>English</hi> thus.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I Stephen</hi> Bishop of Winchester, do purely of mine own voluntary accord, and absolutely in the word of a Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shop, profess and promise to your Princely Majesty, my singular and chief Lord and Patron, <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth, by the grace of God King of England and of France, Defender of the Faith, Lord of Ireland, and in earth of the Church of England Supreme Head immediately under Christ; That from this day forward I shall swear, promise, give, or cause to be given, to no forein Potentate, Emperour, King, Prince, or Prelate, nor yet to the Bishop of Rome, whom they call Pope, any Oath or Fealty directly or indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly, either by word or writing; but at all times, and in every case and condition, I shall observe, hold, and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, to all effects and intents, the quarrel and cause of your Royal Majesty and your Successors, and to the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termost of my power shall defend the same against all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of persons, whomsoever I shall know or suspect to be Adversaries to your Majesty, or to your Successors; and shall give my faith, truth, and obedience, syncerely and with my very heart, onely to your Royal Majesty as to my Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Prince.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Stephen Garde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner</hi> abrenoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth the Pope.</note> I profess the Papacy of Rome not to be or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained of God by holy Scripture, but constantly do affirm and openly declare, and shall declare it, to be set up onely by Man, and shall cause diligently other men likewise to publish the same. Neither shall I enter any Treaty with any person or persons, either privily or apertly, or shall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent thereto, that the Bishop of Rome shall have or exercise here any Authority or Iurisdiction, or is to be restored to any Iurisdiction hereafter.</p>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:58659:5"/>
                  <p>Furthermore, that the said Bishop of Rome now being, or any that shall succeed him hereafter in the said See, is not to be called Pope, nor Supreme Bishop, or Vniversal Bishop, nor most holy Lord, but onely ought to be called Bishop of Rome, and Fellow Brother, (as the old manner of the most ancient Bishops hath been.) This I shall to my power openly maintain and defend.</p>
                  <p>And I shall firmly observe, and cause to be observed of other, to the uttermost of my cunning, wit, and power, all such Laws and Acts of this Realm, how and whatsoever, as have been enacted and established for the extirpation and suppression of the Papacy, and of the Authority and Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>risdiction of the said Bishop of Rome. Neither shall I appeal hereafter to the said Bishop of Rome, nor ever con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent to any person that shall appeal to him; neither shall I attempt, prosecute, or follow any Suit in the Court of Rome, for any cause of right or justice to be had, or shall make answer to any Plea or Action, nor shall take upon me the person and office either of the Plaintiff or Defendent in the said Court. And if the said Bishop by his Messen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, or by his Letters, shall make any means or significa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion unto me, of any matter whatsoeuer it be, I shall with all speed and diligence make declaration and advertise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment thereof, or cause the same to be signified either to your Princely Majesty, or to some of your secret Council, or to your Successors, or any of their privy Council. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther shall I send or cause to be sent at any time any wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting or messenger to the said Bishop or to his Court, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the knowledge or consent of your Majesty or your Successors, willing me to send writing or messenger unto him. Neither shall I procure or give counsel to any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son to procure Bulls, Briefs, or Rescripts whatsoever, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for me or for any other, from the said Bishop of Rome or his Court. And if any such shall be procured against my will and knowledge, either in general or in special, or else howsoever they shall be granted unto them, I shall ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and disclose the same, and not consent thereunto, nor use them in any case, and shall cause them to be brought to your Majesty or your Successors.</p>
                  <p>Furthermore, for the confirmation hereof I give my faith and truth by firm promise, and in the faith of a Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shop, that against this my foresaid Profession and Promise made I shall defend my self by no Dispensation, Excepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, nor any remedy or cautel of Law or Example, during this my natural life. And if heretofore I have done or made any Protestation in prejudice of this my Profession and Promise here made, the same I do revoke at this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent, and for ever hereafter, and here utterly do renounce
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:58659:5"/> by these presents. Whereunto I have subscribed and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derwritten the name both of my self and of my Bishop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick with my proper hand, and thereto also have put to my Seal, in perpetual and undoubted testimony of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>misses.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>Given</hi>
                        <date>
                           <hi>the tenth day of February, Anno 1534, and of our So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereign Lord King Henry the eighth twenty six.</hi>
                        </date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>Stephanus Wintoniensis.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="reasons">
               <head>The same Bishop of <hi>Winchester</hi>'s Reasons against the Pope's Supremacy.</head>
               <p>MOreover the said <hi>Gardener</hi> in the forenamed Book <hi>De vera Obedientia,</hi> what Constancy he pretendeth,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Steph. Wint.</hi> a Lutheran in his Book <hi>De vera obedientia.</hi>
                  </note> what Arguments he inferreth, how earnestly and pithily he disputeth on the Kings side against the Vsurped State of the Bishop of Romes Authority, by the words of his Book it may appear; whereof a brief Collection here fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth.</p>
               <p>IN the process of his foresaid Book,<note place="margin">The Sword of the Church how far it ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendeth.</note> he alledging the old distinction of the Papists, wherein they give to the Prince the Regiment of things Temporal, and to the Church of things Spiritual; comparing the one to the greater Light, the other to the lesser Light, he confuteth and derideth the same distinction, declaring the Sword of the Church to extend no further, than to Teaching and Excommunication, and referreth all preheminence to the Sword of the Prince; alledging for this the second Psalm, <hi>And now you Kings be wise,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Psal 2.</note>
                  <hi>and be learned ye that judge the earth, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Also the example of <hi>Salomon,</hi> who being a King,<note place="margin">2 Par. 28.</note>
                  <hi>accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to his Fathers appointment ordained the Offices of the Priests in their Ministeries, and Levites in their Order,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Exod. 32.</note>
                  <hi>that they might give thanks and minister before the Priests, after the order of every day, and Porters in their divisions gate by gate.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And speaking more of the said <hi>Salomon</hi> he saith, <hi>For so commanded the Man of God,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Reg. 22.</note>
                  <hi>neither did the Priests nor Levites omit any thing of all that he had commanded, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Besides this, he alledgeth also the example of King <hi>Eze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chias,</hi> 2 <hi>Paralyp.</hi> 28. He alledgeth moreover the example and fact of <hi>Justinian,</hi> which made Laws touching the Faith, Bishops, Clerks, Hereticks, and such other.</p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:58659:6"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Aaron</hi> (saith he) obeyed <hi>Moses, Salomon</hi> gave sentence upon <hi>Abiathar</hi> the High Priest.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">1 Macch. 10. 1 Macch. 14.</note>
                  <hi>Alexander</hi> the King (in the first of <hi>Macchabees</hi>) writeth thus to <hi>Jonathas, Now have we made thee this day the High Priest of thy people, &amp;c.</hi> So did <hi>Demetrius</hi> to <hi>Simon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then coming to the words of <hi>Christ</hi> spoken to <hi>Peter, Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew</hi> 16.<note place="margin">Matth. 16.</note> upon which words the Pope pretendeth to build all his Authority, to this he answereth, That if Christ by those words had limited to <hi>Peter</hi> any such special state or preheminence above all Princes, then were it not true that is written, <hi>Coepit Jesus docere &amp; facere;</hi> forasmuch as the words of Christ should then be contrary to his own facts and example, who in all his life never usurped either in himself any such domination above Princes, shewing him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self rather subject unto Princes; nor yet did ever permit to his Apostles any such example of ambition to be seen, but rather rebuked them for seeking any manner of Majority amongst them.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The Kings Style and Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle approved by <hi>Steph. Wint.</hi>
                  </note>And where he reasoneth of the Kings Style and Title, being called the King of England and of France, Defender of the Faith, Lord of Ireland, and Supreme Head in earth of the Church of England immediately under Christ, &amp;c. thus he addeth his mind and censure, saying, That he seeth no cause in this Title why any man should be offend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that the King is called the Head of the Church of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, rather than of the Realm of England; and addeth his reason thereunto, saying, If the Prince and King of England be the Head of his Kingdom, that is, of all Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lishmen that be his Subjects, is there any cause why the fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e English Subjects should not be subject to the same Head likewise in this respect because they are Christians, that is to fan, for the title of Godliness, as though that God, which is the cause of all Obedience, should now be the cause of Rebellion?</p>
               <p>At length thus he concludeth with an Exclamation say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, To say (saith he) that a King is the Head of a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and not of the Church, what an absurd and a foolish saying is this?</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The King is as well the Head of the Church as of his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom.</note>And further, adding for example the subjection of the Servant and Wife. If the Servant (saith he) be subject to his Master, or Wife to her Husband, being Infidels, doth their Conversion afterward, or name of Christians, make them less Subjects than they were before? As Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion therefore doth not alter the Authority of the Master over the Servant, nor of the Husband over the Wife; no more (saith he) doth it between the Prince and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects.</p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:58659:6"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Paul</hi> making no exception nor distinction of Subjection, save onely of that which belongeth to God, willeth all men to obey their Princes; and what Princes? Those Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces which bear the sword. And although we are bound by the Scripture to obey our Bishops and Spiritual Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stors of the Church, yet that obedience diminisheth nothing the chief and head Authority that ought to be given to the Prince, no more than the obedience of the Servant to his Master, or of the Wife to her Husband, exempteth them from Subjection due to their Superiour Powers.</p>
               <p>And herewithall he inferreth a principle of the Law;<note place="margin">A Rule of the Law.</note> Divers Iurisdictions (saith he) proceeding from one person do not marry nor hinder themselves, but rather do con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm and fortifie one another.</p>
               <p>Again, whereas the Bishop of Rome under the name of <hi>Peter</hi> doth appropriate to himself the highest place in the Church, for that he is the Successor of <hi>Peter.</hi> Thereunto he answereth in one word, but in that one word he an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swereth enough and to the full; I would (saith he) he were,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Wenchesters</hi> with that the Pope were <hi>Peters</hi> Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessor.</note> for so in very déed he might well exceed and pass all Kings and Princes, if not in preheminency of Dignity, yet in ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration and excellency of Virtue; in which kind of supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riority the Lord Christ would his Apostles and Ministers to go before all Kings and Emperours in the whole world.</p>
               <p>After this,<note place="margin">Argument: The Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive was gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessed. Flesh and Bloud in <hi>Peter</hi> did not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fess Christ. <hi>Ergo</hi> the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative was not given to the Flesh and Bloud of <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>r.</hi>
                  </note> in prosecuting the Argument of <hi>Peters</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession, he argueth thus and saith; that as flesh and bloud did not reveal to <hi>Peter</hi> that Confession, so neither was that Prerogative given to the flesh and bloud of <hi>Peter,</hi> but to the better part, that is, to the spirit of <hi>Peter,</hi> which is to mean, in respect of the spiritual Confession of <hi>Peter,</hi> and not in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect of any carnal place or person, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Item,</hi> If the Scholar ought not to be above the Master, how then could either <hi>Peter</hi> take▪ that upon him, which Christ his Master so constantly did refuse? Or how can the Bishop of Rome now claim that by Succession, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of no example is to be found either in the Head, or his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>decessor before him? For so we read in <hi>Eusebius,</hi> both of <hi>Peter, James,</hi> and <hi>John,</hi> that they did arrogate no such Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy unto them, but were content that <hi>James</hi> surnamed <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stus</hi> should be the Bishop of the Apostles.</p>
               <p>And as for the name and signification of the word <hi>Prima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus, i.</hi> Primacy, if it be taken for the first nomination,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Primatus</hi> or Primacy what it signifieth.</note> or the first place given, so he granteth that <hi>Peter</hi> had the prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the first name and place in the order of the Apostles; but it followeth not, that with this Primacy he had also a Kingdom given.<note place="margin">He saith, <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm thy Breth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren,</hi> but not thy Subjects.</note> And though he were bid of the Lord to confirm his Brethren, yet was he not bid to exercise an Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery upon his Brethren, for so were they not his Brethren but his Subjects.</p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:58659:7"/>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Primus Prima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus, i.</hi> Primacy meaneth as much as the fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>st standing in Vocation, and is the name of Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue and not of Power.</note>That <hi>Peter</hi> was <hi>Primus,</hi> that is first or chief in the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of them which confessed Christ, it is not to be denied; for first he confessed, first he taught the Iews, first he stood in defence of the Verity, and was the first and chief Prolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutor among them; but yet that maketh not that he should therefore vindicate a general Primacy and Rule over all other States and Potentates of the world, no more than <hi>Apelles,</hi> because he is noted the first and chief of all Paint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, therefore ought to bear rule over all Painters; or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause the Vniversity of Paris is nominate for the first and chief of other Vniversities, shall therefore the French King and all other Princes, in their publick Administration wherein they are set of God, become Subjects and Vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings to that Vniversity?</p>
               <p>Thus after many other reasons and persuasions contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the said Book <hi>De obedientia,</hi> (for I do but superficially skim over the top onely of his Probations and Arguments) finally in the end of his Peroration he concludeth the whole summ of his mind in this effect; first denying that the Bishop of Rome had ever any such extern Iurisdiction assigned to him absolutely from God, to reign over Kings and Princes; for the probation whereof he hath alledged sufficiently (as he saith) the examples and doings of Christ himself, which ought to be us all a sufficient Docu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p>And as concerning the term of Primacy, albeit it be used sometimes of the Fathers, yet the matter being well consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered and rightly expounded, maketh nothing for the large Dominion of the Bishop of Rome, which now he doth usurp.</p>
               <p>Also as for the Prerogatives granted unto <hi>Peter,</hi> by the which Prerogatives our Saviour would crown his own Gifts given unto him, crowning not the flesh and bloud of <hi>Peter,</hi> but the marvellous testimony of his Confession, all this maketh nothing for the Popes purpose.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Succession of <hi>Peter.</hi>
                  </note>Likewise as concerning the Local Succession of <hi>Peter,</hi> the Pope hath nothing thereby to claim. If he will be Successor of <hi>Peter,</hi> he must succeed him in Faith, Doctrine, and Conditions; and in so doing he neither will, neither yet shall need to seek for Honour, but shall be honoured of all good men, according as a good man should be, and that much more than he being a good man would require.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Steph. Wint.</hi> takes his <hi>Vale</hi> of the Pope, but not his <hi>Ʋltimum Vale.</hi>
                  </note>And thus <hi>Stephen Winchester</hi> taking his leave, and bid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the Pope farewell, endeth with a friendly Exhortati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, willing him to be wise and circumspect, and not to strive stubbornly against the truth. The light of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spel (saith he) so spreadeth his beams in all mens eyes, that the works of the Gospel be known, the Mysteries of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:58659:7"/> Christs Doctrine are opened, both learned and unlearned Men and Women, being English born, do see and perceive that they have nothing to do with Rome, nor with the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shop of Rome, but that every Prince in his own Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is to be taken and accepted as a Vicar of God, and Vice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerent of Christ in his own bounds. And therefore seeing this Order is taken of God, and one in the Church should bear the Office of Teaching,<note place="margin">The Office of Teaching.</note> another should bear the Office of Ruling.<note place="margin">The Office of Ruling.</note> (which Office is onely limited to Princes) he exhorteth him to consider the truth, and to follow the same, wherein consisteth our true and special Obedience, &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:lang="lat" type="letter">
               <head>A Letter of the University of <hi>Cambridge</hi> against the Usurped Power of the Bishop of <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>UNiversis Sanctae Matris Ecclesiae filiis, ad quos praesentes Literae perventurae sunt, coetus omnis regentium &amp; non regentium Academiae Cantabrigiensis, salutem, in omnium sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vatore Jesu Christo.</p>
               <p>Cum de Romani Pontificis potestate, &amp;c.</p>
               <div xml:lang="eng" type="translation">
                  <head>Translated into <hi>English</hi> thus.</head>
                  <p>TO all and singular Children of the holy Mother Church, to whose hands these presents shall come,<note place="margin">A Letter of the Universi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge.</hi>
                     </note> the whole Society of Regents and not Regents of the Vniver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sity of Cambridge, sendeth greeting in our Saviour Iesus Christ.</p>
                  <p>Whereas now of late it hath risen up in question among us concerning the Power of the Bishop of Rome, which he doth both claim to himself by the holy Scripture, over all Provinces and Nations in Christendom, and hath now of long time exercised in this Realm of England: And forasmuch as our Censure concerning the cause is requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, to wit, Whether the Bishop of Rome hath any Power or Authority in this Kingdom of <hi>England</hi> allotted to him by God in the Scripture, more than any other forein Bishop, or no? We thought it therefore good reason, and our duty for the searching out of the verity of the said Question, that we should imploy therein our whole endeavour and study, whereby we might tender and publish to the world what our reason and censure is touching the premisses.
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:58659:8"/> For therefore we suppose that Vniversities were first pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided and instituted of Princes, to the end that both the people of Christ might in the Law of God be instructed, and also that false Errors (if any did rise) might through the vigilant care and industry of learned Divines be discussed, extinguished, and utterly rooted out. For the which cause we in our Assemblies and Convocations (after our accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stomed manner) resorting and conferring together upon the Question aforesaid, and studiously debating and delibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rating with our selves, how and by what order we might best proceed for the finding out of the truth of the matter; and at length choosing out certain of the best learned Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors and Batchelors of Divinity, and other Masters, have committed to them in charge, studiously to insearch and peruse the places of holy Scripture, by the viewing and conferring of which places together, they might certifie us what is to be said to the Question propounded.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">The Censure of the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versity of <hi>Cambridge</hi> against the Popes Supre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy.</note>Forasmuch therefore as we having heard and well advi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, and throughly discussed in open Disputations, what may be said on both parts of the foresaid Question, those Reasons and Arguments do appear to us more probable, stronger, truer, and more certain, and sounding much more near to the pure and native sense of Scripture, which do deny the Bishop of Rome to have any such power given him of God in the Scripture. By reason and force of which Arguments we being persuaded, and conjoyning together in one Opinion, have with our selves thus decreed to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer unto the Question aforesaid, and in these writings thus resolutely do answer in the name of the whole Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versity, and for a Conclusion undoubted do affirm, approve, and pronounce,<note place="margin">The Bishop of <hi>Rome</hi> hath no more State in <hi>England</hi> than hath any other Bishop.</note> That the Bishop of Rome hath no more State, Authority, and Iurisdiction given him of God in the Scriptures over this Realm of England, than any other extern Bishop hath. And in testimony and credence of this our Answer and Affirmation, we have caused our common Seal to be put to these our foresaid Letters ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>At Cambridge in our Regent House,</hi>
                        <date>
                           <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 1534.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="testimonies">
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:58659:8"/>
               <head>The publick and general Agreement of the whole Clergy of <hi>England,</hi> confirmed and ratified in their own publick Book called <hi>The Bishops Book, Anno</hi> 1534. with the Names of the Witnesses.</head>
               <p>WE think it convenient,<note place="margin">Testimonies out of the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shops Book again<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t the Popes Supre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy.</note> that all Bishops and Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers shall instruct and teach the People commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted unto their spiritual charge, that whereas certain men do imagine and affirm, that Christ should give unto the Bishop of Rome power and authority, not onely to be Head and Governour of all Priests and Bishops in Christs Church, but also to have and occupy the whole Monarchy of the World in his hands, and that he may thereby law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully depose Kings and Princes from their Realms, Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions, and Seigniories, and so transfer and give the same to such persons as him liketh, that is utterly false and untrue; for Christ never gave unto S. <hi>Peter,</hi> or unto any of the Apostles or their Successors, any such Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. And the Apostles S. <hi>Peter</hi> and S. <hi>Paul</hi> do teach and command, that all Christian People, as well Priests and Bishops, as others, should be obedient and subject unto the Princes and Potentates of the World, although they were Infidels.</p>
               <p>And as for the Bishop of Rome, it was many hundred years after Christ before he could acquire or get any Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy or Governance above any other Bishops out of his Province in Italy; since the which time he hath ever usurped more and more. And though some part of his power was given to him by the consent of the Emperours, Kings and Princes, and by the consent also of the Clergy in General Councils assembled; yet surely he attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the most part thereof by marvellous subtilty and craft,<note place="margin">How the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shop of <hi>Rome</hi> rose by ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> and especially by colluding with great Kings and Princes, sometime training them into his Devotion by pretence and colour of Holiness and Sanctimony, and sometime con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>straining them by force and tyranny. Whereby the said Bishops of Rome aspired and rose at length unto such greatness in Strength and Authority, that they presumed and took upon them to be Heads,<note place="margin">Concilium ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium Cartha i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nense cap. <hi>6.</hi>
                  </note> and to put Laws by their own Authority, not onely unto all other Bishops within Christendom, but also unto the Emperours, Kings, and other the Princes and Lords of the world, and that under
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:58659:9"/> the pretence of the Authority commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted unto them by the Gospel;<note place="margin">
                     <p>First, the General Council of <hi>Nice</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed, that the Patriarchs of <hi>Alexandria</hi> and <hi>Antiochia</hi> should have like power over the Countries about those Cities, as the Bishops of <hi>Rome</hi> had over the Countries about <hi>Rome.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>In the Council of <hi>Milevitan</hi> it was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed, that if a Clerk of <hi>Africk</hi> would ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal out of <hi>Africk</hi> un<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>o any Bishop be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the Sea, he should be taken as a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son Excommunicate.</p>
                     <p>In the General Council of <hi>Constantinople</hi> the first it was likewise decreed, that eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Cause between any persons should be determined within the Provinces where the matters did lie; and that no Bishop should exercise any power out of his own Diocese or Province. And this was also the mind of holy S. <hi>Cyprian,</hi> and of other holy men of <hi>Africa.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>To conclude, therefore the Pope hath no su<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>h Primacy given him, either by the words of Scripture, or by any General Council, or by common consent of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Catholick Church.</p>
                  </note> wherein the said Bishops of Rome do not onely abuse and pervert the true sense and meaning of Christs Word, but they do also clean contrary to the use and cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stom of the Primitive Church, and so do manifestly violate as well the holy Canons made in the Church immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately after the time of the Apostles, as also the Decrees and Constitutions made in that behalf by the holy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of the Catholick Church assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled in the first General Councils. And finally, they do transgress their own profession made in their Creation. For all the Bishops of Rome always, when they be consecrated and made Bishops of that See, do make a so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn profession and vow, that they shall inviolably ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve and keep all the Ordinances made in the first eight General Councils; among the which it is specially provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and enacted, that all Causes shall be finished and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined within the Province where the same begun, and that by the Bishops of the same Province, and that no Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shop shall exercise any Iurisdiction out of his own Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince:<note place="margin">Gregorius l. <hi>4.</hi> Epistolarum indictione <hi>13.</hi> Epist <hi>13.</hi>
                  </note> and divers such other Canons were then made and confirmed by the said Councils to repress and take away out of the Church all such Primacy and Iurisdiction over Kings and Bishops, as the Bishops of Rome pretend now to have over the same. And we find that divers good Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, Bishops of Rome, did greatly reprove, yea and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hor (as a thing clean contrary to the Gospel, and the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees of the Church) that any Bishop of Rome, or else<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, should presume, usurp, or take upon him the Title and Name of Vniversal Bishop, or of the Head of all Priests, or of the Highest priest, or any such like Title. For confirmation whereof it is out of all doubt, that there is no mention made neither in Scripture, nor in the Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of any authentical Doctor or Author of the Church, being within the time of the Apostles, that Christ did ever make or institute any distinction or difference to be in the preheminence of Power, Order, or Iurisdiction, between the Apostles themselves, or between the Bishops themsel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ves, but that they were all equal in Power, Order, Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, and Iurisdiction. And that there is now, and since the time of the Apostles, any such diversity or differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence among the Bishops, it was devised by the antient Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:58659:9"/> of the Primitive Church, for the conservation of good order and unity of the Catholick Church, and that either by the consent and authority, or else at the least by the permission and sufferance of the Princes and Civil Powers for the time ruling, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>And shortly after followeth, And for the better confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this part, we think it also convenient that all Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shops and Preachers shall instruct and teach the people committed unto their spiritual charge, that Christ did by express words prohibit, that none of his Apostles, nor any of their Successors, should, under the pretence of the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority given unto them by Christ, take upon them the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the Sword; that is to say, the Authority of Kings, or of any Civil Power in this world, yea or any Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority to make Laws or Ordinances in causes appertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing unto Civil Powers. Truth it is, the Priests and Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shops may execute all such Temporal Power and Iurisdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as is committed unto them by the Ordinance and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of Kings, or other Civil Powers, and by the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent of the people, (as Officers and Ministers under the said Kings and Powers) so long as it shall please the said Kings and People to permit and suffer them so to use and execute the same. Notwithstanding if any Bishop, of what estate or dignity soever he be, be he Bishop of Rome, or of any other City, Province, or Diocese, do presume to take upon him Authority or Iurisdiction in causes or mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters which appertain unto Kings, and the civil powers and their Courts, and will maintain or think that he may so do by the Authority of Christ and his Gospel, although the Kings and Princes would not permit and suffer him so to do; no doubt that Bishop is not worthy to be called a Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shop, but rather a Tyrant,<note place="margin">The Bishop of <hi>Rone</hi> judged to be a Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant and U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surper.</note> and as Vsurper of other mens rights contrary to the Law of God, and is worthy to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted none otherwise than he that goeth about to subvert the Kingdom of Christ. For the Kingdom of Christ in his Church is a spiritual, and not a carnal Kingdom of the world; that is to say, the very Kingdom that Christ by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self or by his Apostles and Disciples sought here in this world, was to bring all Nations from the carnal King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of the Prince of darkness unto the light of his spiritual Kingdom, and so himself to reign in the hearts of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple by grace, faith, hope, and charity. And therefore sith Christ did never seek nor exercise any worldly Kingdom or Dominion in this world, but rather refusing and flying from the same, did leave the said worldly Governance of Kingdoms, Realms, and Nations, to be governed by Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and Potentates, (in like manner as he did find them) and commanded also his Apostles and Disciples to do the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:58659:10"/> semblable, as it was said before; whatsoever Priest or Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shop will arrogate or presume to take upon him any such Authority, and will pretend the Authority of the Gospel for his defence therein, he doth nothing else but (in a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner as you would say) crowneth Christ again with a Crown of Thorn, and traduceth and bringeth him forth again with his Mantle of Purple upon his back, to be mocked and scorned of the world, as the Iews did to their own dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.</p>
               <p>This Doctrine was subscribed and allowed by the wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness and testimony of these Bishops and other Learned Men, whose Names here under follow, as appeareth in the Bishops Book before named.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <list>
                        <head>TESTES.</head>
                        <item>
                           <note place="margin">Testimonies of Bishops and Doctors of <hi>England</hi> against the Pope.</note>
                           <hi>Thomas Cantuariensis</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Edouardus Eboracensis</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Johannes Londonensis</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Cuthbertus Dunelmensis</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Stephanus Wintoniensis</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Robertus Carliolensis</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Johannes Exoniensis</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Johannes Lincolniensis</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Johannes Bathoniensis</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Rolandus Coventr. &amp; Lichfield.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Thomas E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>iensis</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Nicolaus Sarum</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Johannes Bangor.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Edouardus Herefordiensis</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Hugo Wigorniensis</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Johannes Roffensis</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Richardus Cicestrensis</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Gulielmus Menevensis</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Robertus Assavensis</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Robertus Landavensis</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Guil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>elmus Norwicensis</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Richardus Wolman Archidia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con. Sudbur.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Guilielmus Knight Archidia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con. Richmond.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Johannes Bell Archidiacon. Gloucester.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Edmundus Bonner Archidia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con. Leicester.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Guilielmus Skippe Archidia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con. Dorset.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Nicolaus Heth Archidiacon. Stafford.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Cuthbertus Marshall Archidia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con. Nottingham.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Richardus Curt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>n Archidia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con. Oxon.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Guilielmus Glife</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Galfridus Dounes</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Robertus Oking</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Radulphus Bradford</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Richardus Smith</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Simon Matthew</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Johannes Prin</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Guilielmus Buckmaster</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Guilielmus May</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Nicolaus Wotton</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Richardus Cox</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Johannes Edmunds</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Thomas Robertson</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Johannes Baker</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Thomas Barret</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Johannes Hase</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Johannes Tyson.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </signed> These were Doctors of Divinity and both Laws.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="protestation">
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:58659:10"/>
               <head>A Protestation in the name of the King, and the whole Council and Clergy of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> why they refuse to come to the Popes Council at his call.</head>
               <p>SEeing that the Bishop of Rome calleth Learned Men from all parts, conducting them by great rewards,<note place="margin">The Kings Protestation why he sends not to the Popes Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil.</note> making as many of them Cardinals as he thinketh most m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t, and most ready to defend Frauds and Vntruths; we could not but with much anxiety cast with our selves, what so great a preparance of Wits should mean. As chance was we guessed even as it followed. We have been so long acquainted with Romish Subtilties and Popish Deceits,<note place="margin">The Popes craft espied.</note> that we well and easily judged the Bishop of Rome to intend an Assembly of his Adherents, and men sworn to think all his Lusts to be Laws; we were not deceived. <hi>Paul</hi> the Bishop of Rome hath called a Council, to the which he knew well either few or none of the Christian Princes could come; both the time that he indicted it, and also the place where he appointed it to be, might assure him of this. But whither wander not these Popish Bulls? whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wander they not astray? What King is not cited and summoned by a proud Minister and Servant of Kings, to come to bolster up Errors, Frauds, Deceits, and Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truths, and to set forth this feigned General Council? For who will not think that <hi>Paul</hi> the Bishop of Rome goeth sooner about to make men believe that he pretendeth a Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Council, than that he desireth one indeed? No, who can less desire it, than they that do despair of their Cause, except they be Iudges and give sentence themselves against their Adversaries?<note place="margin">The King not bound to come at the Popes call.</note> We which very sore against our will at any time leave off the procurement of the Realm any common weal, need neither to come our selves, nor yet to send any Procurators thither, no nor yet to make our Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuse for either of both. For who can accuse us that we come not at his call, which hath no Authority to call us?</p>
               <p>But for a season let us (as a sort of Blindlings do) grant that he may call us, and that he hath Authority so to do; yet (we pray you) may not all men see, what availeth it to come to this Council,<note place="margin">Who be they that have place in the Popes Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil.</note> where ye shall have no place except ye be known both willing to oppress truth, and also ready to confirm and stablish Errors? Do not all men perceive as well as we, with what integrity, fidelity, and religion,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:58659:11"/> these men go about to discuss matters in controversie, that take them in hand in so troublesom a time as this is? Is it not plain what fruit the Commonweal of Christendom may look for there,<note place="margin">The place of the Council not indiffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nt.</note> whereas Mantua is chosen the place to keep his Council in? Is there any Prince not being of Italy, yea is there any of Italy, Prince or other dissenting from the Pope, that dareth come to this Assembly and to this place? If there come none that dare speak for trodden truth, none that will venture his life, is it mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel if the Bishop of Rome being Iudge,<note place="margin">No reason that the Pope should be Judge in his own cause.</note> no man repining, no man gainsaying, the Defenders of the Papacy obtain that Popish Authority, now quailling and almost fallen, to be set up again.</p>
               <p>Is this the way to help things afflict? to redress trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled Religion? to lift up oppressed truth? Shall men this way know whether the Roman Bishops (which in very deed are,<note place="margin">The Bishop of <hi>Rome</hi> in learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and life far under other Bishops.</note> if ye look upon either their Doctrine or Life, far under other Bishops) ought to be made like their Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows, that is, to be Pastors in their own Diocese, and so to use no other power; or else whether they may make Laws, not onely unto other Bishops, but also to Kings and Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours? O boldness, meet to be beaten down with force, and not not to be convinced with Arguments. Can either <hi>Paul</hi> that now Lordeth, or any of his, earnestly go about (if they alone, or at the least without any Adversary, be thus in a corner assembled together) to heal the Sicknesses, to take away the Errors, to pluck down the Abuses that now are crept into the Church, and there be bolstered up by such Councils as now is like to be at Mantua?</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Paul</hi> the Pope proleth for his own pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit.</note>Is it very like that these, which prole for nothing but profit, will right gladly pull down all such things as their Forefathers made, onely for the increase of Money? Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as their Forefathers, when their Honour, Power, and Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy was called into question, would either in despight of Gods Law maintain their Dignity, or (to say better) their intolerable Pride? Is it like that these will not tread in their steps, and make naughty new Canons, whereby they may defend old evil Decrees? Howbeit, what need we to care either what they have done, or what they intend to do hereafter,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>England</hi> ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth her leave of the Pope for ever.</note> forasmuch as England hath taken her leave of Popish Crafts for ever, never to be deluded with them here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after? Roman Bishops have nothing to do with English People; the one doth not traffick with the other, at least though they will have to do with us, yet we will none of their merchandise, none of their stuff, we will receive them of our council no more.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>England</hi> refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth the Popes Merchandise.</note> We have sought our hurt, and bought our loss a great while too long. Surely their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees, either touching things set up or put down, shall have
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:58659:11"/> none other place with us than all Bishops Decrees have, that is, if we like them we admit them, if we do not we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuse them. But lest peradventure men shall think us to follow our senses too much, and that we moved by small or no just causes, forsake the Authority, Censures, Decrees, and Popish Counsels, we thought it best here to shew our mind to the whole world. Wherefore we protest before God and all men, that we embrace, profess, and will ever so do, the right and holy Doctrine of Christ. All the Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of his Faith, no jot omitted, be all so dear unto us, that we should much sooner stand in jeopardy of our Realm, than to see any point of Christs Religion in jeo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pardy with us.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>England</hi> goeth not from the unity of Faith although it goeth from the Pope.</note> We protest that we never went from the unity of his Faith, neither that we will depart an inch from it. No, we will much sooner lose our Lives, than any Article of our Belief shall decay in England. We, which in all this cause seek nothing but the glory of God, the profit and quietness of the World,<note place="margin">The Faith of <hi>England</hi> Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick. <hi>England</hi> ready to send to any General Council where truth may be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced.</note> protest that we can suffer Deceivers no longer. We never refused to come to a General Council; no, we promise all our labour, study, and fidelity, to the setting up of trodden Truth and trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled Religion in their place again, and to do all that shall lie in us to finish such Controversies as have a great while too long vexed Christendom. Onely we will all Christian men be admonished, that we can suffer no longer that they be esteemed willing to take away Errors, which indeed by all the ways their Wits will serve them go about this alone, that no man under pain of Death may speak against any Error or Abuse.</p>
               <p>We would have a Council, we desire it, yea and crave no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing so oft of God as that we may have one. But yet we will that it be such as Christian men ought to have, that is, frank and free, where every man without fear may say his mind. We desire that it be an holy Council,<note place="margin">What a true General Council ought to be.</note> where eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man may go about to set up Godliness, and not apply all their study to oppressing of Truth. We will it be Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, that is to say, kept at such time and in such place, that every man which seeketh the glory of God may be present, and there frankly utter his mind. For when it shall seem General,<note place="margin">Conditions of a true Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Council.</note> either when no man that dissenteth from the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shop of Rome is compelled to be from it, or when they that be present are not letted by any just terror to say boldly what they truly think; for who would not gladly come to such a Council, except it be the Pope, his Cardinals, and Popish Rishops? On the other side, who is so foolish, whereas the chief point that is to be handled in this Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil is the Popes own Cause, Power, and Primacy, to grant that the Pope should reign, should be Iudge, should be Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sident
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:58659:12"/> of the Council? If he which indeed can never think himself able to defend his Cause before any other Iudge,<note place="margin">The Pope would be Judge in his own cause.</note> be evermore made his own Iudge, and so Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versies not decided, but Errors set up, what can be devised in the Commonwealth of Christendom more hurtful to the truth than General Councils?</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The Pope hath no pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to summon Councils.</note>And here to touch somewhat their impudent Arrogancy; By what Law, Power, or honest Title take they upon them to call Kings, to summon Princes to appear, where their Bulls command them? In time past all Councils were appointed by the Authority, Consent, and Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Emperour, Kings, and Princes; why now ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth the Bishop of Rome this upon him? Some will say, It is more likely that Bishops will more tender the cause of Religion, gladlier have Errors taken away, than Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours, Kings, and Princes. The world hath good expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience of them, and every man seeth how faithfully they have handled religious matters. Is there any man that doth not see how vertuously <hi>Paul</hi> now goeth about by this occasion to set up his Tyranny again?<note place="margin">The Pope how he can watch his time.</note> Is it not like that he that chooseth such a time as this is to keep a Council, much intendeth the redress of things that now are amiss, that he seeketh the restoring of Religion, that now calleth a Council, the Emperour and the French King, two Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of great power, so bent to Wars that neither they, nor any other Christian Prince can, in a manner do any thing but look for the end of this long War? Go too, go t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o, Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shop of Rome, occasion long wish'd for offereth her self unto you; take her, she openeth a Window for your Frauds to creep in at: call your Cardinals, your own Creatures, shew them that this is a jolly time to deceive Princes in.</p>
               <p>O Fools! O wicked men! may we not justly so call you? Are ye not Fools, which being long suspected not onely of Princes, but of all Christian People in a manner, that in no case you could be brought to a General Council, plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly shew the whole world, that by these your Conciliables, your Hutter-mutter in corners, you take away all hope of lawful Catholick and General Council? Are you not wicked which so hate Truth, that except she be utterly ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nished ye will never cease to vex her?<note place="margin">Truth may be pressed it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> be op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressed.</note> The living God is alive, neither Truth his Dearling (he being alive) can be called to so great shame, contumely, and injury; or if it may be called to all these, yet can it come to none of them. Who is he that grievously lamenteth not men to be of such shameful boldness,<note place="margin">The Pope Enemy to Christ.</note> to shew apertly that they be Enemies unto Christ himself? On the other side, who will not be glad to see such men as foolish as they be wicked? The World is not now in a light suspicion, as it hath been hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:58659:12"/> that you intend no reformation of Errors, but eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man seeth before his eyes your deceits, your wicked minds,<note place="margin">The Popes hatred against the truth.</note> your immortal hatred that ye bear against the Truth. Every man seeth how many miserable Trage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies your pretence of an Vnity and Concord hath brought into Christendom. They see your fair face of Peace hath served Sedition, and troubled almost all Christian Realms.<note place="margin">The Pope troubler of all Christian Realms.</note> They see ye never oppugn Religion more, than when ye will seem most to defend it. They be sorry to see that great Wits a long season have spent their whole strength in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of Deceits, Reason to put his whole power to the promoting of Pride and Vngodliness, Vertues to serve Vices, Holiness to be slave to Hypocrisie, Prudence to Subtilty, Iustice to Tyranny. They be glad that Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture now fighteth for it self, and not against it self. They be glad that God is not compelled to be against God, Christ against Christ. They be glad that Subtilty hath done no more hurt to Religion in time past, than now Constancy doth do good to Truth.<note place="margin">The Popes marks where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at he shoot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth.</note> They see the Marks that ye have shot at in all your Councils past, to be Lucre, Money, Gains; they see you sought your Profit, yea though it were joyn'd with the Slaughter of Truth. They see ye would ever that sooner injury should be done to the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spel, than that your Authority, that is to say, arrogant Impudency should in any point be diminished.</p>
               <p>And we pray you,<note place="margin">The Popes craft in steal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a General Council.</note> what may <hi>Paul</hi> the Bishop of Rome seem now to go about, which seeing all Princes occupied in great affairs, would steal (as he calleth it) a General Council? What other thing, than hereby to have some excuse to refuse a General Council hereafter, when time and place much better for the handling of matters of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion shall be given unto Princes of Christendom? He will think he may then do as Princes now do; he will think it lawful not to come then, because Princes now come not. We pray God that we ever brawl not one with another in Religion; and whereas Dissention is amongst us, yet for our parts we do say, that we as much as men may, defend the better part, and be in the right way. We pray God that the world may enjoy peace and tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quillity, and that then we may have both time and place to settle Religion. For except first Princes agree, and so (War laid aside) seek peace, he loseth his labour that seeketh a General Council. If the Bishop of Rome may keep his Council while they thus be together, will not there be made many pretty Decrees? If they which would come if they had leisure be absent, and we which (though we safely might come) will not lose any part of our right, trow you in all our absence that the Bishop of Rome will not handle his Profit and Primacy well?</p>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:58659:13"/>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The time and pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>esent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly picked of the Pope.</note>
                  <hi>Paul,</hi> how can any of ours not refuse to come to Mantua, through so many perils, a City so far set from England, so nigh your Friends, Kinsmen, and Adherents? Is he not unworthy of Life, that where he may tarry at home, will pass through so many Ieopardies of Life? Can he which cometh to Cremona, a City not far from Mantua, be safe if he be taken not to be the Bishop of Romes Friend,<note place="margin">What an He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retick is among the Papists.</note> that is, (as the common sort of deceived people doth interpret) an Heretick? And if there come to Mantua such a number as would furnish a General Council, may not Mantua seem too little to receive so many Guests? Put these two toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, all the way from England to Mantua is full of just pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rils, and yet if ye escape all those, the very place where the Council is kept is more to be suspected than all the way. Do ye not know all Civil Laws to compel no man to come to any place, where he shall be in jeopardy of his Life all the way? We have no safe conduct to pass and return by the Dominions of other Princes. And if we had a safe conduct, yet should not we be charged with rashness, that where just terror might have dissuaded us from such a journey,<note place="margin">The way to <hi>Mantua</hi> long and d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous.</note> we committed our selves to such perils? Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly he that (the time being as it is, things standing as they do) will go from England to Mantua, may be careless if he lack not wit; sure of his arrival or return from thence he cannot be. For who doth not know how oft the Bishops of Rome have plaid false parts with them that in such matters have trusted to their safe conduct? How oft have they caused by their Perfidie such men to be slain,<note place="margin">The falshood of Popes no new thing.</note> as they have promised by their Faith before, that they should both come safe and go safe? These be no news, Popes to be false, Popes to keep no promise neither with God nor Man; Popes contrary to their oaths, to defile their cruel hands with honest mens bloud. But we tarry too long in things that as well touch all men as us.</p>
               <p>We will (these now laid apart) turn our Oration unto such things, as privately touch both us King <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth, and all Englishmen. Is it unknown to any man what mind <hi>Paul</hi> the Bishop of Rome beareth to us King <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth, to us his Nobility, to us his Graces Bishops, and to us all his Graces Subjects, for the pulling down of his usurped Power and proud Primacy, for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelling of his usurped Iurisdiction, and for delivering of our Realm from his grievous bondage and pollage? Who seeth not him even enflamed with hatred against us,<note place="margin">The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>atred of the Pope against <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
                  </note> and the flames to be much greater than he can now keep them in? He is an open Enemy, he dissembleth no longer, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voking all men by all the means that he can, to endamage us and our Country. These three years he hath been oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupied
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:58659:13"/> in no one thing so much, as how he might stir up the Commons of England, and corrupting some with Money, some with Dignities. We let pass what Letters he hath written to Christian Princes; with how great fervent study he hath exhorted them to set upon us. The good Vicar of Christ by his doing sheweth how he understands the words of Christ; he thinketh he playeth Christ's part well, when he may say as Christ did, <hi>Non veni pacem mittere in terram,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The Pope bringeth not peace but the sword to the earth, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise than Christ did.</note>
                  <hi>sed gladium;</hi> I come not to make peace in earth, but to send swords about: and not such swords as Christ would his to be armed withall, but such as cruel Manquellers abuse in the slaughter of their Neighbours. We marvel little though they vex'd other Princes oft, seeing they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence our favour shewed to them with contumelies, our benefits with injuries.</p>
               <p>We will not rehearse here how many our Benefits be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stowed upon Roman Bishops be lost;<note place="margin">Benefits cast away upon the Pope.</note> God be with such ungrate Carles, unworthy to be numbered amongst men; Certes such that a man may well doubt whether God or Man hath better-cause to hate them. But that we have learned to owe good will even to them that immortally hate us, what could we wish them so evil but they have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>served much worse? We wish them this hurt alone, that God send them a better mind. God be thanked we have made all their seditious intents sooner to shew their great malice towards us, than to do us much hurt; yea, they have well taught us evermore to take good heed to our Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies. Vndoubtedly it were good going to Mantua, and to leave their Whelps among the Lambs of our Flock. When we be weary of our Wealth, we will even do then as they would have us now do. No, no, as long as we shall see his heart so good towards us, we trust upon his warn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing we shall well provide to withstand his cruel malice. No let him now spend his deceits, when they can hurt none but such as would deceive and are deceived.</p>
               <p>They have by sundry ways made us privy how much we be bound to them. It went nigh their hearts to see the judgment of <hi>July,</hi> of <hi>Clement</hi> the seventh, of <hi>Paul</hi> the third, nothing to be regarded with us. They be afraid if we should sustain no hurt, because we justly rejected their Primacy, that other Princes would begin to do likewise,<note place="margin">The Popes Curses not seared in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
                  </note> and to shake from their shoulders the heavy burthens that they so long have born, against Scripture, all right and reason. They be sorry to see the way stopped, that now their Tyranny, Avarice, and Pride can have no passage into England, which was wont to walk, to triumph, to toss, to trouble all men. They can scarce suffer Privile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, that is to say, Licence to spoil our Citizens, given
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:58659:14"/> them by our Forefathers, and brought in by errorfull Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stom, to be taken from them. They think it unlawful, that we require things lawful of them that will be under no Laws. They think we do them wrong because we will not suffer them to do us wrong any longer. They see their Merchandize to be banished,<note place="margin">The Popes Trumpery dispatched out of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
                  </note> to be forbidden; they see that we will buy no longer Chalk for Cheese. They see that they have lost a fair fleece, vengeable sorry that they can dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patch no more Pardons, Dispensations, Totquots, with the rest of their baggage and trumpery. England is no more a Babe; there is no man here but now he knoweth that they do foolishly that give Gold for Lead,<note place="margin">Gold given for Lead.</note> more weight of that than they receive of this; they pass not, though <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Pauls</hi> Faces be graven in the Lead to make Fools fain. No, we be sorry that they should abuse holy Saints Visages to the beguiling of the world.</p>
               <p>Surely, except God take away our right wits, not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly his Authority shall be driven out for ever, but his Name also shall be forgotten in England.<note place="margin">God grant.</note> We will from henceforth ask councel from him and his when we list to be deceived, when we covet to be in error, when we desire to offend God, Truth and Honesty. If a man may guess the whole work by the foundation,<note place="margin">The Popes foundation to all deceits.</note> where Deceits begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the work, can any other than Deceits be builded up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this foundation? What can you look for in this Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuan Council, other than the oppression of Truth and true Religion? If there be any thing well done, think as eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man doth, Bishops of Rome to be accustomed to do a few things well, that many evil may the better be taken at their hands.<note place="margin">The Pope doth a few things well, that many evils may the bet er pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed.</note> They when they list can yield some part of their right; they are content that some of their Decrees, some of their Errors and Abuses be reprehended, but they are never more to be feared than when they shew them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves most gentle. For if they grant a few they ask ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, if they leave a little they will be sure of a great deal. Scarce a man may know how to handle himself, that he take no hurt at their hands, yea when they bless him; which seldom do good but for an intent to do evil. Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly, come who so will to these Shops of Deceits, to these Fairs of Frauds,<note place="margin">The Pope ought to be called, and not to call.</note> we will lose no part of our right in coming at his call, that ought to be called and not to call. We will neither come at Mantua, nor send thither for this matter, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>And so the King proceeding in the said his Protestation declareth moreover, how the Pope after he had summoned his Council first to be kept at Mantua,<note place="margin">The Pope again pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regnes his Council.</note> the three and twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieth day of May, An. 1537, shortly after directed out ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Bull to prorogate the same Council to the moneth of
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:58659:14"/> November, pretending for his excuse that the Duke of Mantua would not suffer him to keep any Council there, unless he maintained a number of Warriours for defence of the Town. And therefore in his later Bull he proro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gueth this Assembly, commanding Patriarchs, Archbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shops, Bishos, Abbats, and other of the Spiritualty, by the vertue of Obedience, and under pain of Cursing, to be present, but sheweth no place at all where he would be, nor whither they should come. And in very deed no great matter though no place were named; for as good a Council no where to be called, as where it could not be; and as well no place served him that intended no Council, as all places. And to say truth, much better no place to be na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, than to name such as he purposed not to come to; for so should he break no promise which maketh none. And so going forward in his Oration, toward the later end he thus inferreth by his words of Protestation, saying:</p>
               <p>No,<note place="margin">Princes as they gave the Pope Prima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, so they take it from him again.</note> we will the Pope and his Adherents to understand that which we have oft said, and now say, and ever will say. He nor his hath no Authority nor Iurisdiction in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land; we give him no more than he hath, that is never a deal. That which he hath usurped against Gods Law, and extorteth by violence, we by good right take from him again. But he and his will say, we gave them a Prima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy. We bear them well, we gave it you indeed; if you have Authority upon us as long as our Consent giveth it you, and you evermore will make your plea upon our Consent, then let it have even an end where it began; we consent no longer, your Authority must needs be gone. If we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing deceived by false pretence of evil-alledged Scriptures, gave to you that ye ought to have refused, why may we not, our Error now perceived, and your Deceit espied, take it again? We Princes wrote our selves to be inferiour to Popes; as long as we thought so we obeyed them as our Superiours. Now we write not as we did, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they have no great cause to marvel, if we hereafter do not as we did; both the Laws Civil, and also the Laws of God, be on our side. For a Freeman born doth not lose his Liberty, no nor hurt the plea of his Liberty, though he write himself a Bondman.</p>
               <p>Again, if they lean to Custom,<note place="margin">Custom.</note> we send them to S. <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prian,</hi> which saith, That Custom, if Truth be not joyned with it, is nothing but <hi>Erroris vetustas,</hi> that is, an old Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror. Christ said, <hi>Ego sum via, veritas, &amp; vita;</hi> I am the way, the truth, and the life: he never said, <hi>Ego sum con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suetudo,</hi> I am the Custom. Wherefore seeing Custom ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth you on the one side, and Scripture us on the other, are ye able to match us? In how many places doth
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:58659:15"/> Christ monish you to seek no Primacy, to prefer your selves before nobody, no to be obedient unto all Creatures? Your old Title <hi>Servus Servorum</hi> evil agreeth your new forged Dignity.<note place="margin">The Popes Title and his Dignity agree not together.</note> But we will not tarry in matters so plain; we onely desire God, that <hi>Caesar,</hi> and other Christian Princes, would agree upon some holy Council, where truth may be tried, and Religion set up, which hath been hurt by no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing so sore, as by general not General Councils. Errors and Abuses grow too fast; <hi>Erudimini qui judicatis terram,</hi> Get you Learning you that judge the earth; and excogi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate some Remedy for these so many Diseases of the sick Church. They that be wisest do despair of a General Council;<note place="margin">Best that eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Prince re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form his own Realm, and tarry not for General Councils.</note> wherefore we think it now best that every Prince call a Council Provincial, and every Prince to redress his own Realm. We make all men privy what we think best to be done for the redress of Religion: if they like it, we doubt not but they will follow it, or some other better. Our trust is, that all Princes will so handle themselves in this behalf, that Princes may enjoy their own, and Priests of Rome content themselves with that they ought to have. Princes as we trust will no longer nourish Wolves Whelps, they will subscribe no more to Popish Pride, to the Papacy, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Favour our doings, O Christian Princes, your Honour and ancient Majesty is restored. Remember there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing peetaining so much to a Princes Honour, as to set forth Truth, and to help Religion. Take you heed that their Deceits work not more mischief than your Vertue can do good, and everlasting War we would all Princes had with this Papacy. As for their Decrees, so hearken to them, that if in this Mantuan Assembly things be well done ye take them, but not as authorized by them, but that Truth, and things that maintain Religion, are to be taken at all mens hands. And even as we will admit things well made, so if there be any thing determined in prejudice of Truth, for the maintainance of their evil grounded Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy, or that may hurt the Authority of Kings, we protest unto the whole world, that we neither allow it, nor will at any time allow it.</p>
               <p>Ye have, Christian Readers, our mind concerning the General Council; we think you all see that <hi>Paul</hi> and his Cardinals, Bishops, Abbats, Monks, Friers, with the rest of the Rabblement, do nothing less intend, than the Knowledge of Truth. Ye see this is no time meet, Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tua no place meet for a General Council; and though they were both meet, yet except some other call this Council, you see that we neither need to come nor to send. You have heard how every Prince in his own Realm may quiet
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:58659:15"/> things amiss. If there be any of you that can shew us a better way, we promise with all our hearty desire to do that that shall be thought best for the settling of Religion, and that we will leave our own Advices if any man shew us better. Which mind of ours we most heartily pray God that gave it us, not onely to increase in us, but also to send it unto all Christian Princes, all Christian Prelats, and all Christian People.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="injunctions">
               <head>Injunctions given by King <hi>Henry</hi> VIII. to the Clergy of his Realm.</head>
               <p>IN the Name of God, Amen. In the Year of our Lord God <hi>1536,</hi> and of the most Noble Reign of our Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Lord <hi>Henry VIII.</hi> King of England and of France, Defender of the Faith, Lord of Ireland, and in the earth Supreme Head of the Church of England, the twenty eighth, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>I <hi>Thomas Cromwell</hi> Knight, Lord <hi>Cromwell,</hi> Kéeper of the Privy Seal of our said Sovereign Lord the King, and Vicegerent to the same; for and concerning all his Iuris<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction Ecclesiastical within this Realm, to the glory of Almighty God, to the Kings Highness Honour, the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick weal of this Realm, and increase of Vertue in the same, have appointed and assigned these Injunctions en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suing, to be kept and observed of the Dean, Parsons, Vicars, Curats, and Stipendaries, resident or having Cure of Souls, or any other Spiritual Administration within this Deanry, under the Pains hereafter limited and appointed.</p>
               <p>THE first is, that the Dean, Parsons, Vicars, and other having Cure of Souls any where within this Deanry, shall faithfully keep and observe, and as far as in them may lie, shall cause to be kept and observed of all other, all and singular Laws and Statutes of this Realm, made for the abolishing and extirpation of the Bishop of Romes pretended and usurped Power and Iurisdiction within this Realm,<note place="margin">Confirmation of the Kings Supremacy.</note> and for the establishment and confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of the Kings Authority and Iurisdiction within the same, as of the Supreme Head of the Church of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, and shall to the uttermost of their Wit, Knowledge,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:58659:16"/> and Learning, purely, syncerely, and without any colour or dissimulation, declare, manifest, and open, by the space of one quarter of a year now next ensuing, once every Sunday, and after at the least twice every quarter of a year, in their Sermons and other Collations, that the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shop of Romes Vsurped Power and Iurisdiction,<note place="margin">Again<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t the Popes Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy.</note> having no establishment nor ground by the Law of God, was for most just causes taken away and abolished, and that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they owne unto him no manner of Obedience or Subje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and that the Kings Power is within his Dominion the highest Potentate and Power under God, to whom all men within the same Dominion, by Gods commandment owe most Loyalty and Obedience, afore and above all other Potentates in earth.</p>
               <p>Item, Whereas certain Articles were lately devised and put forth by the Kings Highness Authority, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>descended unto by the Prelats and Clergy of this his Realm in Convocation, (whereof part were necessary to be holden and believed for our Salvation, and the other pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t do concern and touch certain laudable Ceremonies, Rights, and Vsages of the Church, meet and convenient to be kept and used for a decent and politick order in the same) the said Dean, Parsons, Vicars, and other Curats, shall so open and declare, in their Sermons and other Collati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, the said Articles unto them that be under their Cure, that they may plainly know and discern which of them be necessary to be believed and observed for their Salvation, and which be not necessary, but onely do concern the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent and politick order of the said Church, according to such commandment and admonition as hath been given unto them heretofore by the Authority of the Kings High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness in that behalf.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The Kings Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles to be read to the people.</note>Moreover, that they shall declare unto all such as be under their Cure, the Articles likewise devised, put forth, and authorized of late, for and concerning the abrogating of certain superstitious Holydays, according to the effect and purport of the same Articles, and persuade their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rishioners to keep and observe the same inviolably, as things wholsom, provided, decreed, and established by the common Consent and publick Authority, for the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weals commodity and profit of all this Realm.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Images abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lished.</note>Besides this, to the intent that all Superstition and Hypocrisie crept into divers mens hearts may vanish away, they shall not set forth or extoll any Images, Reliques, or Miracles, for any superstition or lucre, nor allure the peo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:58659:16"/> by any intreatments to Pilgrimages of any Saints,<note place="margin">Pilg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="5 letters">
                        <desc>•••••</desc>
                     </gap> forbidden▪</note> otherwise than is permitted in the Articles lately put forth by the Authority of the Kings Majesty, and conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scended unto by the Prelats and Clergy of this his Realm in Convocation, as though it were proper or peculiar to that Saint to give this Commodity or that; seeing all G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>od<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, Health, and Grace, ought to be both looked and ask<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for onely of God, as of the very Author of the same, and of none other, for without him it cannot be given; but they shall exhort as well their Parishioners as other Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grims, that they do rather apply themselves to the keeping of Gods Commandments, and the fulfilling of his works of Charity; persuading them that they shall please God more by the true exercise of their bodily Labour, Travel, or Occupation, and providing for their Families, than if they went about to the said Pilgrimages; and it shall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit more their Souls health, if they do bestow that on the poor and needy, which they would have bestowed upon the said Images or Reliques.</p>
               <p>Also in the same their Sermons and other Collations,<note place="margin">Prayers in the Mother Tongue.</note> the Parsons, Vicars, and other Curats aforesaid, shall di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently admonish the Fathers and Mothers, Masters and Governours of Youth, being within their Cure, to teach or cause to be taught their Children and Servants, even from their Infancy, the <hi>Pater noster,</hi> the Articles of our Faith, and the Ten Commandments in their Mother Tongue, and the same so taught shall cause the said Youth oft to repeat and understand. And to the intent this may be the more easily done, the said Curats shall in their Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons deliberately and plainly recite of the said <hi>Pater no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster,</hi> Articles, or Commandments, one Clause or Article one day, and another another day, till the whole be taught and learned by little and little, and shall deliver the same in writing, or shew where printed Books containing the same be to be sold to them that can read, or will desire the same; and thereto that the said Fathers and Mothers, Masters and Governours, do bestow their Children and Servants, even from their Childhood, either to Learning or to some honest Exercise, Occupation, or Husbandry; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horting, counselling, and by all the ways and means they may, as well in their said Sermons and Collations, as otherwise, the said Fathers, Mothers, Masters, and other Governours, being under their cure and charge, diligently to provide and foresee,<note place="margin">For bringing up of Youth in some Art or Occupati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> that the said Youth be in no manner wise kept or brought up in idleness, lest at any time after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward they be driven, for lack of some Mystery or Occupati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to live by, to fall to begging, stealing, or some other
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:58659:17"/> unthriftiness; forasmuch as we may daily see, through sloth and idleness divers valiant men fall, some to begging, some to theft and murther, which after brought to calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and misery, impute a great part thereof to their Friends and Governours, which suffered them to be brought up so idly in their Youth; where if they had been brought up and educated in some good Literature, Occupation or Mystery, they should (being Rulers of their own Families) have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fited as well themselves as divers other persons, to the great commodity and ornament of the Commonweal.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Placing of good Vicars and Curats.</note>Also that the said Parsons, Vicars, and other Curats, shall diligently provide, that the Sacraments and Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentals be duly and reverently ministred in their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rishes. And if at any time it happen them, either in any of the cases expressed in the Statutes of this Realm, or of special Licence given by the Kings Majesty, to be absent from their Benefices, they shall leave their Cure not to a rude and unlearned person, but to an honest, well learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and expert Curat, that may teach the rude and unlearn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of their Cure wholsom Doctrine, and reduce them to the right way, that they do not erre; and always let them sée, that neither they nor their Vicars do seek more their own profit, promotion, or advantage, than the profit of the Souls that they have under their Cure, or the glory of God.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Every Parish to provide a Bible in English.</note>Item, that every Parson or Proprietary of any Parish Church within this Realm, shall on this side the Feast of S. <hi>Peter ad vincula</hi> next coming, provide a Book of the whole Bible both in Latin and also in English, and lay the same in the Quire, for every man that will to look and read thereon, and shall discourage no man from the read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of any part of the Bible, either in Latin or English, but rather to comfort, exhort, and monish every man to read the same as the very Word of God, and the spiritual food of mans Soul, whereby they may the better know their Duties to God, to their Sovereign Lord the King, and their Neighbour; ever gently and charitably ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horting them, that using a sober and modest behaviour in the reading and inquisition of the true sense of the same, they do in no wise stiffly or eagerly contend or strive one with another about the same, but refer the declaration of those places that be in controversie, to the judgment of them that be better learned.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Priests not to haunt Ale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houses.</note>Also the said Dean, Parsons, Vicars, Curats, and other Priests, shall in no wise at any unlawful time, nor for
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:58659:17"/> any other cause than for their honest necessity, haunt or resort to any Taverns or Alehouses, and after their Din<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner and Supper they shall not give themselves to drinking or riot, spending their time idly by day or by night, at Tables or Cards playing, or any other unlawful Game; but at such times as they shall have such leisure, they shall read or hear somewhat of holy Scripture, or shall occupy themselves with some honest Exercise, and that they al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways do those things that appertain to good congruence and honesty, with profit of the Commonweal, having al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways in mind that they ought to excell all other in purity of life, and should be example to all other to live well and Christianly.</p>
               <p>Furthermore, because the goods of the Church are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the goods of the Poor, and in these days nothing is less seen than the Poor to be sustained with the same, all Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, Vicars, Prebendaries, and other beneficed men with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in this Deanry, not being resident upon their Benefices, which may dispend yearly twenty pounds or above, either within this Deanry, or else where, shall distribute hereafter yearly amongst their poor Parishioners or other Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants there, in the presence of the Churchwardens, or some other honest men of the Parish, the fortieth part of the Fruits and Revenues of their said Benefices, lest they be worthily noted of Ingratitude, which reserving so many parts of themselves, cannot vouchsafe to impart the forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth portion thereof amongst the poor people of that Parish that is so fruitful and profitable unto them.</p>
               <p>And to the intent that learned men may hereafter spring the more, for the executing of the said premisses, every Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, Vicar, Clerk, or beneficed man within this Deanry, yearly to spend in Benefices or other Promotions of the Church, an hundred pounds, shall give competent Exhibiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to one Scholar; and for as many hundred pounds more as he may dispend, to so many Scholars more shall give like Exhibition in the Vniversity of Oxford or Cambridge, or some Grammar School; which after they have profited in good Learning, may be Partners of their Patrons Cure and Charge, as well in Preaching, as otherwise in the execution of their Offices, or may when <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ed shall be other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise profit the Commonwealth with their counsel and wisdom.</p>
               <p>Also that all Parsons, Vicars, and Clerks, having Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, Chapels, or Mansions within this Deanry, shall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stow yearly hereafter upon the same Mansions or Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels of their Churches being in decay, the fifth part of
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:58659:18"/> those their Benefices, till they shall be fully <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and the same so repaired they shall always <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> as good estate.</p>
               <p>All which and singular Inj<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ng <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 words">
                     <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> be inv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="7 letters">
                     <desc>〈7 letters〉</desc>
                  </gap> observed of the said <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Parso<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Curats. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ndaries, and other Clerks, and beneficed man, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> pain of Suspension, and S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>stration of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of their Benefices, untill they have done their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="6 letters">
                     <desc>••••••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing to these Injunction<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>